"lang" { 
"Language" "polish" 
"Tokens" 
{
"#commentary\tf2-Comment000.wav"   "[Gabe Newell] Witamy w Team Fortress 2. Pracowaliśmy nad tą grą 9 lat. Mamy nadzieję, że również Twoim zdaniem warto było na nią poczekać. Aby uaktywnić dany komentarz, nakieruj celownik na symbol w grze, a następnie naciśnij klawisz używania. Aby zatrzymać komentarz, nakieruj celownik na obracający się symbol komentarza i ponownie naciśnij klawisz używania. Niektóre komentarze po uaktywnieniu przejmują chwilowo kontrolę nad grą, aby ukazać bliżej dany szczegół. W takim przypadku wystarczy ponownie nacisnąć klawisz używania, aby zatrzymać komentarz.  Gdy już zagrasz, napisz mi o swoich wrażeniach. Jestem osiągalny pod adresem gaben@valvesoftware.com. Przy okazji — moja ulubiona klasa to szpieg. Dzięki i dobrej zabawy!"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment000.wav"   "[Gabe Newell] Welcome to Team Fortress 2. After nine years in development, hopefully it will have been worth the wait. To listen to a commentary node, put your crosshair over the floating commentary symbol and press your use key. To stop a commentary node, put your crosshair over the rotating node and press the use key again. Some commentary nodes may take control of the game in order to show something to you. In these cases, simply press your use key again to stop the commentary.  Please let me know what you think after you have had a chance to play. I can be reached at gaben@valvesoftware.com, and my favorite class is the spy. Thanks, and have fun!"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment001.wav"   "[Jeremy Stone] W grach wieloosobowych zawartość, na której działają gracze, w dużej części jest tworzona przez innych graczy.  Aby wspomóc ten proces, dodaliśmy funkcje mające na celu promowanie współpracy między graczami. Na przykład migawka zabójcy gracza pomaga temu graczowi zapamiętać konkretnych, najbardziej kłopotliwych przeciwników.  Funkcja mściciela wprowadza dodatkowe przypomnienie, że niektórzy wrogowie są ważniejsi niż inni.  Tworzy ona niewielką ujemną pętlę wzmacniającą — oferuje graczom możliwości zdobycia dodatkowych punktów za zabicie przeciwnika w odwecie."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment001.wav"   "[Jeremy Stone] In multiplayer games, the content players consume is largely generated by other players.  To enhance this, we added features designed to promote relationships between players.  
For example, the freeze-cam shot of a player's killer helps the player remember specific, troublesome opponents.  The nemesis feature adds an additional reminder that certain enemies are more significant than others.  It creates a small negative reinforcement loop by giving players an opportunity to score extra points with a revenge kill.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment002.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] Granice na mapach muszą być nieprzekraczalne. Jeśli jednak środowisko nie jest ograniczone do zamkniętych pomieszczeń czy kanionów o wysokich pionowych ścianach, granice nie zawsze blokują widok na otaczający teren znajdujący się poza zasięgiem. W naszych bardziej realistycznych grach, np. HL2, granice te często wymagają fikcyjnych/wizualnych objaśnień. W wysoce stylizowanym świecie Team Fortress widoczna sztuczność jest jednym z podstawowych założeń gry, dlatego możemy uprościć albo w ogóle zrezygnować z takich wyjaśnień bez negatywnego wpływu na jakość samego grania. Testy pokazały na przykład, że niskie ogrodzenia oddzielające pole gry od pustego otaczającego terenu skutecznie sugerowały, że obszar za ogrodzeniem jest mało ciekawy i nic się na nim nie dzieje."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment002.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] Maps require impassable boundaries, but unless we restrict the environments to either interior spaces or steep canyons, these boundaries can't always block the player's view of the outlying, unreachable area. In our more realistic titles, like HL2, these boundaries often require fictional and visual explanations. In the heavily stylized Team Fortress world, however, conspicuous artificiality is a core design principle and so we can simplify or altogether ignore these explanations without compromising the player experience. Playtesting showed, for instance, that these low fences leading to an empty expanse successfully conveyed the message that the area beyond the fence is uninteresting and out-of-bounds."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment003.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] Każda klasa w grze Team Fortress pełni unikatową rolę w ofensywie i defensywie. Zadaniem punktów kontrolnych jest zasadniczo skoncentrowanie uwagi graczy na tych podstawowych działaniach zaczepnych i obronnych. Pomagają również ściągać graczy do różnych punktów na mapie."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment003.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] Each of the Team Fortress classes was designed to make a unique contribution to attack and defense, and control points are, fundamentally, methods of focusing players' attention on these core offensive and defensive activities. They're also useful for drawing players to different points of the map."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment004.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] W pierwotnym projekcie gdy napastnicy zostali odparci z danego punktu, tracili cały teren uzyskany przy zdobywaniu tego miejsca. Testy pokazały, że samotni gracze znajdujący się w pobliżu punktów kontrolnych przeciwnika nie mieli żadnej motywacji, aby próbować go zdobyć, jeśli w pobliżu znajdowały się jakiekolwiek siły wroga. Ponadto gdy drużyna została zepchnięta do obrony tylko jednego punktu kontrolnego, silniejsza drużyna atakująca często nie była w stanie zdobyć tego punktu w wyznaczonym czasie, w efekcie czego gry kończyły się patem. Dlatego zmieniliśmy zasady zdobywania. Teraz operacja trwa jeszcze chwilę po odstąpieniu atakujących od punktu kontrolnego. Korekta pozwoliła usunąć oba problemy występujące w pierwotnym projekcie."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment004.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] In our original design, once attackers were cleared off a point, they lost any progress they'd made toward capturing the point. Playtests revealed that lone players near an enemy control point had no incentive to try to capture it if any enemies were in the area. Furthermore, once a team was reduced to defending a single control point, the stronger attacking team was often unable to successfully assault the final point for the full capture period, which caused too many games to end in a stalemate. We changed the capture mechanic so that capture progress persists for a while even after the attackers are cleared off the point, and this improvement fixed both of the problems with the original design.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment005.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] Aby umożliwić graczom podejmowanie ciekawszych decyzji nawigacyjnych, trasy na mapie powinny mieć różną efektywność bazującą na aktualnej klasie gracza i stanie mapy. Utrudnieniem na trasach może być woda, ponieważ pływanie jest wolniejsze od biegu. Na takie utrudnienia często godzą się szpiedzy, ponieważ w ten sposób unikają wykrycia przy infiltrowaniu przeciwnika. Z kolei unikają ich piromani, ponieważ ich podstawowa broń jest pod wodą bezużyteczna. Jeśli przeciwnik dysponuje silną obroną, mimo zwiększonej trudności droga wodna opłaci się klasom, które próbują zajść obrońców od tyłu."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment005.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] To give players interesting navigation decisions, routes through a map should vary in effectiveness based on the player's current class and the state of the map. Water lets us increase the cost of taking a particular route, because swimming is slower than running. Spies often accept that cost in order to infiltrate undetected. Pyros avoid it because their primary weapon is useless underwater. If the enemy has a strong defense, the increased cost of the water route becomes a worthwhile tradeoff for any class trying to hit the defenders from behind."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment006.wav"   "[Iikka Keranen] Trójwymiarowe skyboxy są w skali 1/16, co ma na celu zmniejszenie zużycia pamięci przez zawarte w nich duże przestrzenie. Oznacza to, że w przypadku pociągów jadących między skyboxem a przestrzenią gracza musimy uciec się do małej sztuczki. W rzeczywistości istnieją dwie wersje każdego poruszającego się pociągu: jeden w skali gracza przeznaczony dla faktycznej przestrzeni gry, i drugi, znacznie mniejszy, umieszczony w skyboxie. Małe hangary naprawcze znajdujące się po obu stronach środkowego budynku maskują punkt, w którym podmieniamy pociągi."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment006.wav"   "[Iikka Keranen] We build our 3d skyboxes at 1/16th scale to reduce the memory used by the large spaces in them. This means we have to get a little tricky when dealing with trains moving between the skybox and the player space. There are actually two versions of each moving train; A player-scaled one for the actual gameplay space, and a tiny one out in the skybox. The small repair sheds on either side of the middle building disguise the point at which we swap between the two trains."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment007.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] Najlepiej jest, gdy pojedynki kończą się zwycięstwem jednej i porażką drugiej drużyny. Pat w praktyce jest porażką dla obu drużyn. W celu uniknięcia sytuacji patowych projekt mapy bierze pod uwagę dwie podstawowe zmienne: czasy przegrupowania drużyn oraz czasy przemieszczenia z punktu przegrupowania na linię frontu. Drużyna, która wygrywa, ma nieco krótsze czasy przegrupowania i punkty przegrupowania wysunięte bardziej do przodu. Takie rozwiązanie tworzy dodatnią pętlę wzmacniająca, która zwiększa szanse na skuteczną ofensywę i wygranie gry."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment007.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] Ideally, matches should end in a victory for one team and a loss for the other. Stalemates are essentially a loss for both teams. To avoid stalemates, our map design considers two key variables: team respawn times and travel time from the respawn point to the frontline. The team that's winning gets slightly faster respawn times and more forward respawn points, a positive reinforcement loop that increases the chances for them to push forward and win the game."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment008.wav"   "[Dave RIller] Aby umożliwić działanie snajperom, mapa musi oferować otwarte przestrzenie, długie linie widoku i możliwości osłony.  Osoby będące celami snajperów muszą wybierać alternatywne trasy, które leżą poza liniami widoku snajperów. Zazwyczaj jednak wiążą się z tym dodatkowe niedogodności, np. dłuższy czas podróży.  W związku z tym gracze stoją w obliczu wyboru: czy obrać drogę bardziej bezpośrednią, ale niebezpieczną, czy też bezpieczniejszą, ale dłuższą?  Ponadto zasadniczo dla pozycji snajperów istnieją stanowiska snajperów przeciwnika, umieszczone po drugiej stronie danej sceny. W efekcie snajperzy w dużej mierze równoważą swój wpływ, co zwiększa szanse członków drużyny na bezpieczne przejście przez osłonięty teren."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment008.wav"   "[Dave RIller] To accommodate snipers, maps need wide open spaces, long sightlines, and protective cover.  Targets of the Sniper require alternate routes that bypass the Sniper's sightlines, though these usually have an additional cost, such as increased travel time.  This leaves players with a choice:  do they take the more direct, but hazardous route, or the safer yet slower route?  Sniper positions generally also have a corresponding enemy sniper deck, positioned on the other side of the arena, which allows one sniper to counter another, offering cover for teammates in exposed areas."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment009.wav"   "[Bay Raitt] Sytuacje patowe zdarzają się najczęściej w pobliżu drzwi/bram, gdzie drużyny po obu stronach mają mocne pozycje obronne. Aby zapobiec takiemu rozwojowi wypadków, wprowadziliśmy alternatywne obejścia o wysokim stopniu trudności. Są one warte uwagi tylko wtedy, gdy wróg jest silnie ufortyfikowany na głównej drodze. Kluczowe znaczenie w konstrukcji danego obszaru ma liczba punktów, przez które może dostać się przeciwnik, ponieważ bardzo trudno utrzymać obronę przy przeciwniku nacierającym z wielu stron. Dlatego tak przydatne są jednokierunkowe drogi ewakuacyjne, ponieważ pozwalają oddzielić punkty wejściowe dostępne dla wroga od przyjaznych dróg umożliwiających atak."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment009.wav"   "[Bay Raitt] Stalemates generally occur around doors, where teams have a strong defensive presence on either side of the opening. To help counter this, we provide alternate routes with high travel costs that become more attractive only when the enemy has strong defenses behind the main route. The number of enemy entry points into an area is crucial to its design, since it's extremely hard to hold an area when enemies approach from multiple fronts. This makes one way exits a useful design tool, since they let us uncouple the number of enemy entry points from the number of friendly offensive routes."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment010.wav"   "[Jamaal Bradley] W celu zoptymalizowania przebiegu gry musimy czasami zneutralizować szybkość określonych klas. Dlatego na przykład wprowadzono mechanizm centralnych zegarów otwierania drzwi. Mają one zagwarantować członkom wszystkich klas możliwość dotarcia do środkowej części mapy, zanim rozpocznie się faktyczna akcja Testy pokazały, że gra zyskuje na atrakcyjności, gdy na otwarcie bramy oczekuje cała drużyna. Oczekiwanie na bitwę w połączeniu z niebezpieczeństwem stwarzanym przez jadące pociągi stwarza świetną sytuację wyjściową do walki o centralny punkt kontrolny."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment010.wav"   "[Jamaal Bradley] For gameplay purposes, we sometimes need to neutralize the speeds of the classes. For instance, these central door timers were created to ensure that all classes could make it to the middle part of the map by the time the action actually starts. Playtesting showed that it was more fun to have the teams waiting as a group as soon as the doors open. The anticipation of battle, combined with the hazardous moving trains, creates a great opening clash for the middle control point."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment011.wav"   "[Matt Boone] W mocno bronionych obszarach, np. wokół punktów kontrolnych, warto stosować kuloodporne szkło. Z jednej strony pozwala stronie atakującej widzieć rozmieszczenie obrońców i karabinów strażniczych, z drugiej zaś obrona widzi zbierających się napastników. To bardzo ważne informacje dla obrońców w przypadku, gdy napastnicy oczekują na zastrzyk nieśmiertelności od lekarza."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment011.wav"   "[Matt Boone] Bulletproof glass is a useful design tool in strongly defended areas, such as around control points. It gives the offensive team a chance to see enemy defenders and sentrygun positions, while affording the defensive team a good view of the gathering attackers. This is often crucial for the defense if the offense is waiting for a Medic's invulnerability charge."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment012.wav"   "[Matthew Russell] Na mapach stanowiących teren zmagań zaczepno-obronnych do sytuacji patowej dochodzi zazwyczaj w przypadku, gdy drużyna atakująca ma słabą pozycję i bezradnie bije głową w mur, a czas ucieka. Aby tego uniknąć, wprowadziliśmy mechanizm, zgodnie z którym prawdopodobna porażka szybko zamienia się w prawdziwą porażkę. Zaczynamy od niewielkiego limitu czasu, który jest wydłużany w reakcji na zdobycie punktu przez napastników. Dzięki temu runda kończy się najszybciej, jak to tylko możliwe, a jednocześnie cały czas utrzymuje się napięcie. Długie rundy zupełnie nie pasują do atmosfery koniecznego pośpiechu, jaką chcemy stworzyć w grze."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment012.wav"   "[Matthew Russell] On Attack/Defend maps, stalemates generally involve a weakly positioned attacking team beating its head against the wall as the timer bleeds out. To avoid this, we encourage likely losses to snowball into actual losses as quickly as possible. We start with a short time limit, and then add time whenever the offensive team succeeds in capturing a point. This way the round plays out in as short a time as possible and keeps the tension high throughout. Long round times aren't conducive to the sense of urgency we want to create."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment013.wav"   "[John Cook] Przy projektowaniu budowli obronnych warto korzystać z wysokich ścian. Na przykład budynek B dowództwa musi być broniony ze wszystkich stron. Odpowiednia wysokość i okna na wszystkich ścianach dają obrońcom możliwość skutecznego miotania rakiet i granatów. Kuloodporne szyby w wybranych oknach pozwalają bezpiecznie obserwować zbliżającego się przeciwnika."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment013.wav"   "[John Cook] Height is a useful feature when designing defensible buildings. For instance, the Cap B building needs to be defended from all directions. The height, and windows on all sides, give defenders in this building an advantage, when launching rockets & grenades from within. Bulletproof glass in some windows lets them safely view approaching enemies."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment014.wav"   "[Jake Nicholson ] Dla żołnierzy zaprojektowaliśmy pomieszczenia, w których szczególną uwagę zwrócono na wysokość. Zasadniczo żołnierze wolą strzelać na wrogów z góry, ponieważ wybuchy rakiet sieją wtedy dokoła największe zniszczenie. Taką możliwość stwarza ulokowanie się na dachu. Na dach można się dostać wyłącznie przy użyciu wyrzutni rakiet znajdującej się na wyposażeniu żołnierzy, dzięki czemu jest on praktycznie niedostępny dla członków pozostałych klas. Z powodu szkód wyrządzanych przez odrzut z wyrzutni żołnierze tracą część zdrowia. Kompromis ten w połączeniu z pogorszonym stanem zdrowia w trakcie pobytu na dachu pozwala zredukować część ogromnych zalet dachu bez zakłócania równowagi w walce, ponieważ żołnierze będą potrzebowali pomocy lekarzy znajdujących się na dole."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment014.wav"   "[Jake Nicholson ] For Soldiers, we design spaces with specific attention to height. Soldiers generally want to be shooting down at opponents to maximize the effect of their rockets' splash damage. The rooftop here gives them that advantage. It can also only be reached with the soldier's rocket jump, making it generally inaccessible to the other classes. Because of the splash damage from a rocket jump, soldiers have to trade health for the height advantage. This tradeoff, coupled with the lack of health on the roof, lets usmake the rooftop a powerful advantage without unbalancing the map, since soldiers will need to rely on medics down below to keep them healthy."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment015.wav"   "[Dave Riller] Aby umożliwić działanie klasie zwiadowców, mapy muszą zawierać otwarte przestrzenie pozwalające im na dwukrotnie dłuższe skoki po ścieżkach niedostępnych dla członków innych klas.  Obszar ten charakteryzuje się obecnością różnorodnych dachów i skał, po których zwiadowcy mogą się przemieszczać, cały czas pozostając nad przeciwnikami innymi niż zwiadowcy wroga.  Zwiadowcy często wykorzystują swoją przewagę szybkości do chwilowego wycofania się w celu uzupełnienia zdrowia, dlatego wprowadziliśmy element ryzyka: artefakty ze zdrowiem są umieszczone w niewielkim, zamkniętym obszarze, gdzie istnieją pewne ograniczenia ruchowe."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment015.wav"   "[Dave Riller] To accommodate the scout class, maps need open spaces that allow scouts to double jump along paths that the other classes can't navigate.  This area features a variety of rooftops and rocks that a scout can traverse while staying above any non-scout opponents.  Scouts often use their speed advantage to retreat and collect health, so here we force them to adopt some risk by placing the health inside a small, enclosed area, where they sacrifice some freedom of movement."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment016.wav"   "[Matt Boone] Klasa szpiega jest przeznaczona dla graczy, którzy chcą przechytrzyć swoich przeciwników. Ogólna koncepcja działania szpiega polega na wniknięciu do drużyny przeciwnika, poruszaniu się w przebraniu oraz eliminowania najważniejszych przeciwników — zazwyczaj snajperów, inżynierów i lekarzy — błyskawicznym ciosem noża w plecy. Peleryna-niewidka ma mu pomóc w dwóch kluczowych sytuacjach. Pierwsza to przedarcie się za linię frontu, gdzie gracze są najbardziej wyczuleni na obecność wroga i najbardziej podejrzliwi w przypadku osób poruszających się w niewłaściwym kierunku. Druga to ucieczka przed wrogiem, który przejrzał przez przebranie w czasie, gdy szpieg znajdował się na jego terytorium. Saper, którym dysponuje szpieg, służy do bezpiecznego eliminowania działek strażniczych wroga pozostawionych bez opieki, zmuszając inżynierów do bacznego zwracania uwagi na ich konstrukcje."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment016.wav"   "[Matt Boone] The Spy is designed for players who want to outsmart their opponents. At a high level, his gameplay flow is to infiltrate the enemy team, move around while disguised, and use his instant-kill backstab to take out key enemies, usually snipers, engineers, and medics. His invisibility cloak is designed to help him in two key situations. The first is in getting past the frontline, where players are most vigilant against enemies and most suspicious of friends not heading in the right direction. The second is in escaping from enemies who have seen through his disguise while he's in enemy territory. His sapper was designed to allow him to easily take out unattended enemy sentryguns, forcing enemy engineers to keep a close eye on their buildings."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment017.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Jednym z poważniejszych wyzwań projektowych w Team Fortress 2 było odpowiednie dobranie możliwości karabinów strażniczych inżynierów sterowanych przez sztuczną inteligencję. Jeśli karabin byłby zbyt mocny, tylko najlepsi gracze byliby w stanie mu się przeciwstawić. Jeśli były za słaby, inżynier nie miałby szans w starciu z dobrymi graczami, co podważałoby w ogóle sens budowania takiej broni. Zdecydowaliśmy się na działanie karabinu w sposób w zasadzie binarny, tzn. jest on śmiercionośny dla przeciwników, którzy atakują bez ochrony, ale nie potrafi inteligentnie reagować na wrogów wyskakujących zza jakiejś zasłony. W ten sposób inżynier własną bronią pomocniczą musi rekompensować słabość karabinu w starciach z przeciwnikami działającymi z ukrycia, a jednocześnie karabin pozostaje straszliwą bronią wobec każdego wroga, który próbuje po prostu szybko przed nim przebiec."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment017.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Balancing the strength of the Engineer's AI-controlled sentrygun was one of more difficult design problems in Team Fortress 2. If the gun was too powerful, only the most skilled players would be able to counteract it. If the gun was too weak, the Engineer would have no chance against skilled players, effectively eliminating any reason to build it in the first place. Our solution was to make the sentrygun essentially binary in the sense that it's lethal to opponents who don't take cover, but can't intelligently deal with enemies popping in and out of cover. This forces the Engineer to use his own secondary weapons skill to compensate for the sentrygun's corner weakness, while still making the sentrygun a formidable obstacle for any opponent simply attempting to sprint past it."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment018.wav"   "[Andrew Burke] Klasa zwiadowcy jest adresowana do graczy, którzy chcą mieć możliwość szybkiego przemieszczania się w trakcie śledzenia wybranych obiektów. Podczas gdy inne klasy bojowe koncentrują się na niszczeniu siłą, zwiadowcy unikają ognia przeciwnika dzięki swojej szybkości i możliwości wykonywania dwukrotnie dłuższych skoków. Styl walki jest w dużej mierze zbudowany wokół możliwości ich podstawowej broni — karabinu półautomatycznego. Karabin ten wyrządza znaczne szkody, ale ma duży rozrzut. W efekcie zwiadowca musi podejść bardzo blisko przeciwnika, co wiąże się oczywiście z dużym ryzykiem. Karabin ma niską szybkostrzelność, w wyniku czego zwiadowca musi się zatrzymać, oddać strzał, uchylić się od ognia przeciwnika, wychylić, strzelić, uchylić itd., narażając się w ten sposób na trafienie. Charakteryzuje się również niewielkim magazynkiem i długimi czasami jego zmiany, co ma na celu zachęcenie zwiadowcy do wycofania się z pola walki (bardzo łatwe przy jego szybkości) w celu uzupełnienia amunicji. Rozwiązanie to ma umożliwić rannym wrogom ucieczkę, zanim zwiadowca powróci."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment018.wav"   "[Andrew Burke] The Scout is designed for players who are able to rapidly move around while tracking their target. Where other combat classes rely on high amounts of damage, the Scout relies on his high movement speed and double jump ability to dodge enemy fire. Much of his combat style is crafted through the features of his primary weapon, the scattergun. It does a large amount of damage, but has a wide spread that forces him to get close to the enemy for full effect, where he's also at highest risk of being hurt. It has a slow rate of fire that encourages him to pause to fire, then dodge, then pause, and so on, which gives enemies a higher chance to hit him at intervals. Finally, it holds a small clip and a slow reload time to encourage the Scout to pull out of combat to reload, something which he can do easily with his speed, and gives injured enemies a chance to run before the Scout returns."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment019.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] Żołnierz to podstawowa klasa bojowa wyróżniająca się różnorodnością ruchów i znakomitymi możliwościami wyrządzania szkód na duże odległości. Ma zapewniać sprawność działania niemal w każdej sytuacji bojowej oraz najwyższą skuteczność unikania ognia karabinów strażniczych prowadzonego na duże odległości. Jej największe słabości wynikają z rodzaju używanej broni podstawowej — wyrzutni rakiet. Wyrzutnię wyposażono w mały magazynek, co zmusza żołnierzy do rozsądnego używania ognia. Niska prędkość pocisków znacznie ogranicza przydatność tej broni poza najbliższy zasięg w odniesieniu do przeciwników, którzy dobrze unikają ataku, na przykład wobec szpiegów."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment019.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] The Soldier is a core combat class featuring versatile movement and terrific long range damage capability. He's designed to be comfortable in almost any combat situation, and to be the best long-range anti-sentrygun class. His main weaknesses are designed into his primary weapon, the rocket launcher. It has a small clip size, which forces the Soldier to carefully manage his reloads, and it fires relatively slow-moving projectiles, making it ineffectual beyond short range against any opponent who dodges well, like the Scout."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment020.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] Kolejnym ciekawym zagadnieniem projektowym był karabin snajperski. W odpowiedzi na oczekiwania graczy karabin musi być w stanie zabić przeciwnika jednym strzałem w głowę. Z drugiej strony nie może dawać takiego samego efektu przy szybkim strzale z biodra, ponieważ w rękach doświadczonego gracza stałby się najgroźniejszą bronią krótkiego zasięgu w całej grze, negując podstawową słabość snajperów. Aby rozwiązać ten dylemat, wprowadziliśmy wskaźnik siły rażenia, który pojawia się dopiero po użyciu lunety snajperskiej. Rozwiązanie to przynosi kilka zalet: Niska skuteczność przy braku użycia lunety i zaraz po jej użyciu gwarantuje, że snajperzy nie będą w stanie zabijać wrogów bez odpowiedniego przymierzenia się. Wydłużony proces ładowania oznacza, że snajperzy mogą wybierać między szybkim ogniem o małej skuteczności a strzałami o dużej skuteczności, ale oddawanymi znacznie wolniej, co niesie ryzyko wyeliminowania przez skoordynowany atak drużyny przeciwnika. Najwyższa skuteczność dostępna na końcu skali siły rażenia wymusza zachowania typowe dla snajpera, czyli np. znalezienie dobrego punktu obserwacyjnego i bardzo precyzyjne strzelanie do wybranych ofiar."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment020.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] The sniper rifle was another tricky design problem. To meet players' expectations, a sniper rifle has to be able to kill an opponent with a single shot to the head. On the flip side, we need to ensure it can't be snap fired from the hip with the same effect, because then, in the hands of an experienced player, it also becomes the game's most lethal short range weapon, negating the Sniper's primary weakness. To solve this, we implemented a charging damage meter that only appears when the sniper is zoomed. This solution has several beneficial side effects: 
The low damage both while un-zoomed and at the initial zoom ensures that Snipers can't kill opponents with impromptu snap fire. The charge time means Snipers can deal out low damage shots quickly or highly damaging shots at slow intervals, which allows opponents to overwhelm them with a coordinated rush. The high damage at the end of the charge rewards Sniper-esque behaviors, such as locating a decent vantage point and taking very deliberate shots.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment021.wav"   "[Marc Scaparro] Z założenia Piroman to najlepsza klasa bitewna w starciach na małe odległości, co ma zachęcić graczy to stosowania zasadzek. Piromani są słabo chronieni na otwartym terenie, dlatego muszą się czaić w osłoniętych miejscach, wejściach do pomieszczeń itd. Aby zwiększyć śmiercionośność piromanów w starciach na małych odległościach, efekt miotania płomieni jest teraz rozbudowany wizualnie. Wróg ulega dezorientacji, a w tym czasie niszczą go płomienie."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment021.wav"   "[Marc Scaparro] The Pyro is designed to be the best short-range combat class, aimed at encouraging players to adopt an ambush style of play. To achieve this, we made the Pyro vulnerable in the open, which forces players to seek out enclosed areas and doorways. To add to the Pyro's short range lethality, we made the flamethrower effects visually noisy, which helps disorient opponents long enough for the flames to finish them off."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment022.wav"   "[Wade Schin] Demoman to najbardziej wszechstronna klasa bojowa, oferująca możliwość szybkiego przejścia od intensywnego ataku do silnej obrony. Jako jedyna w grze może prowadzić ogień pośredni, co pozwala na eliminowanie karabinów strażniczych umieszczonych za rogiem. Miny magnetyczne zapewniają możliwość wykonywania skoków przy użyciu granatów w sposób podobny do skoków wykonywanych przez żołnierzy za pomocą wyrzutni rakiet. Min magnetycznych można również używać do blokowania przejść przez drzwi/bramy, osłaniania odwrotu czy obrony punktów kontrolnych nawet w sytuacji, gdy Demoman znajduje się w zupełnie innym miejscu."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment022.wav"   "[Wade Schin] The Demoman is the most versatile combat class, capable of rapidly switching from strong offensive pushes to defensive area denial. He has the only indirect fire capability in the game, allowing him to take out sentryguns around the corner, and his sticky bombs give him a grenade jumping ability similar to that of the Soldier's rocket jumps. His sticky bombs can also prevent enemies from moving through doorways, cover a retreat, and defend control points even when the Demoman is somewhere else."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment023.wav"   "[Keith Huggins] Dzięki szerokiemu polu ostrzału minidziałko postaci Heavy umożliwia udział w walce graczom, którzy średnio radzą sobie z celowaniem. Aby zrekompensować niższy poziom umiejętności celowania u danego gracza, wzmocniliśmy wagę innych umiejętności. Na przykład czas przygotowania do strzału i ograniczona szybkość w trakcie strzelania zmusza graczy do nauczenia się przewidywania zarówno zbliżania się ataków wroga, jak i momentu rozpoczęcia potyczki."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment023.wav"   "[Keith Huggins] With its wide field of fire, the Heavy's minigun lets players who don't have great twitch-aiming skills still wade into the thick of combat. To make up for this reduction in the value of the player's aiming skill, we amplified the importance of other skills. For instance, the wind-up time before firing and the heavy's reduced speed while firing force players to learn to anticipate both the start of combat and incoming enemy attacks."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment024.wav"   "[John Morello] Najważniejszą klasą pomocniczą jest Lekarz. Dotychczasowe klasy pomocnicze miały wiele niedociągnięć. Nie wymagały na przykład wielu umiejętności, ponieważ ich członkowie pozostawali zawsze w bronionych obszarach, tracąc przy okazji możliwość udziału w najciekawszych chwilach gry. Co jednak najgorsze, nie byli szczególnie przydatni, ponieważ przeważnie znajdowali się z dala od graczy, którzy najbardziej potrzebowali pomocy. Klasa lekarza w Team Fortress 2 eliminuje te problemy, głównie dzięki umieszczeniu lekarzy w samym sercu walki. Ponadto obsługa karabinu używanego przez lekarzy została maksymalnie uproszczona, dzięki czemu opatrywanie rannych nie odbywa się kosztem zdolności do obrony własnej. Strzelać można praktycznie bez celowania, co pozwala lekarzom skupić się na osobie wymagającej pomocy. Z kolei leczona osoba ma wszelkie motywy, aby zapewnić maksymalne bezpieczeństwo swojemu lekarzowi."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment024.wav"   "[John Morello] The Medic is the main support class. Previous support classes we've designed had a variety of problems. They didn't require much skill, because they stayed back in defended areas, which also kept them out of the funnest parts of the game. Worst of all, this meant they weren't even terribly useful because they generally weren't near the players who most needed to be healed. We designed the Team Fortress 2 Medic to solve these problems, primarily by focusing on keeping them right in the thick of battle. Additionally, we designed the medigun to be as easy to use as possible, so that Medics can focus on survival while healing teammates. Virtually no aiming is required, which lets Medics concentrate on following their heal target, who has a huge incentive to keep his Medic benefactor safe."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment025.wav"   "[Aaron Halifax] Podstawowym założeniem przy projektowaniu karabinu lekarskiego było stworzenie silnego związku między lekarzem a postacią wymagającą pomocy.  Chcieliśmy zobaczyć, co można osiągnąć dzięki stworzeniu ścisłej więzi między dwoma graczami, zamiast koncentrować się jedynie na zapewnieniu współdziałania większej drużyny.  Konstrukcja karabinu daje gwarancję ścisłej współpracy między lekarzem a jego pacjentem. Pilnują oni nawzajem swojego rozmieszczenia i stanu zdrowia oraz uważnie podejmują taktyczne decyzje.  Chcieliśmy, aby osoba wymagająca opieki zachowywała się w określony, przemyślany sposób. Lekarze szukaliby w pierwszym rzędzie właśnie takich pacjentów.  W ten sposób uzyskujemy związek, na którym nam zależało."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment025.wav"   "[Aaron Halifax] Our main goal in designing the Medigun was to build a strong relationship between the Medic and his healing target.  We wanted to see what we would get if we focused on creating a tight loop between two players, instead of just thinking about getting the larger team to cooperate.  The Medigun's design ensures that the Medic and his target are extremely conscious of each other, watching their health and relative positions, and making tactical choices carefully.  We wanted there to be skill involved in being a good healing target, so that Medics would seek out and latch onto skilled targets.  This helps foster the relationship we were after."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment026.wav"   "[Jakob Jungels] Nieśmiertelność wprowadza element pośpiechu w rozgrywce z udziałem wielu graczy, która zazwyczaj ma mniej momentów napięcia niż dobrze opracowana gra jednoosobowa.  Gdy nieśmiertelny lekarz i jego pacjent wbiegają na pole walki, jest to dla nich bardzo emocjonująca chwila.  Sytuacja taka stawia na nogi również obronę, która wie, że musi wytrzymać przez 10 sekund, zanim nieśmiertelność zniknie.  Nieśmiertelność zwiększa również tempo gry przez umożliwienie stronie atakującej przełamania impasu powstającego w przypadku, gdy obrońcy zaszyją się na swoich stanowiskach i nie chcą podjąć walki w otwartym polu.  Bez konieczności przełamywania umocnień obronnych atakującym łatwiej akumulować punkty nieśmiertelności bez przerywania walki.  Dodatkowo nieśmiertelność to fantastyczny cel, do którego może dążyć lekarz, stanowiąc nagrodę za skuteczne leczenie. W celu wymuszania odpowiednich zachowań lekarz otrzymuje większą liczbę punktów za leczenie osób rannych niż w pełni zdrowych."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment026.wav"   "[Jakob Jungels] Invulnerability adds an element of pacing to the multiplayer experience, which otherwise tends to have fewer emotional highs and lows than a well-crafted single player game.  When an invulnerable Medic & his friend come running in, it's an extreme high point for them.  It's also a rush for the defenders, who know they've just got to hold on for 10 seconds until invulnerability fades.  Invulnerability also sharpens pacing by helping a team push through a defensive stalemate, when the enemy team turtles up and refuses to come out of their base.  Without a lack of defensive skirmishers, it's easier for the offense to build up the invulnerability charge without interruption.  In addition, invulnerability is a great goal for the Medic and rewards him for being an effective healer. We encourage the behavior by adding more charge when the Medic is healing injured teammates than when he's healing ones who are already at full health."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment027.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] W grach wieloosobowych gracze często wykorzystują tylko niewielką liczbę map, powtarzając na nich kolejne rozgrywki.  Dlatego zamiast tworzyć wiele map, z których większość pozostałaby nieużywana, postanowiliśmy opracować jedną mapę, ale z większą atrakcyjnością dla kolejnych rozgrywek, niż kiedykolwiek do tej pory.  W większości map dla gier wieloosobowych jeszcze przed całkowitym załadowaniem wiadomo, jak będzie wyglądała gra.  My chcieliśmy stworzyć mapę, w której nie można przewidzieć nawet tak podstawowej rzeczy jak punkt startu, nie mówiąc już o dalszym przebiegu gry.  Dlatego też stan wyjściowy mapy Hydro jest dobierany losowo.  Ponieważ nacisk jest położony na przejęcie kontroli nad stale zmieniającym się terytorium, gracze rzadko odnoszą wrażenie, iż mapa się powtarza.  Jednocześnie usystematyzowany przebieg każdej rundy gwarantuje stałą koncentrację uwagi członków drużyny i zapewnia wahania emocji, gdy drużyna traci lub zyskuje terytorium."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment027.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] Multiplayer communities tend to focus on a small group of maps, playing them over and over again.  Instead of producing a large number of maps, most of which would go un-played, we decided to try and build a single map with more innate replayability than any we'd built before.  With most multiplayer maps, you know what you'll be doing before the map has even finished loading.  In our case, we wanted a map where you couldn't predict even something as basic as your starting point, let alone what you would be doing when you got there.  Hydro therefore begins with a randomized starting state.  The emphasis on control of constantly shifting territories means the map rarely feels repetitive.  Meanwhile, the explicit round structure keeps teams focused, and provides regular highs and lows as the teams gain and lose territory."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment028.wav"   "[Kerry Davis] Zazwyczaj w grach statystyki polegają na porównaniu osiągnięć danego gracza z innymi osobami na całym świecie.  Takie podejście jest jednak interesujące tylko dla najlepszych graczy.  Dlatego w przypadku TF postanowiliśmy wprowadzić statystyki porównujące osiągnięcia gracza z jego poprzednimi wynikami. W ten sposób dotychczasowy system ogólnoświatowy stał się bardziej osobisty, a przez to motywujący. Początkujący gracz czuje zachętę do podnoszenia umiejętności. Wie, że o ile nie jest jeszcze w gronie najlepszych, cały czas robi postępy. Z kolei weterani zobaczą, czy zbliżyli się do swoich wcześniejszych rekordów, co będzie dla nich zachętą do ich pobicia.  System statystyk osobistych pełni również rolę weryfikacyjną. Gdy gracz uważa, że w danej rundzie spisał się szczególnie dobrze, pojawia się komunikat systemu statystyki z treścią typu „Masz rację, rzeczywiście świetnie Ci poszło.”."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment028.wav"   "[Kerry Davis] Games usually approach stats by comparing the player to everyone else in the world.  This is only really of interest to those who are near the top.  With TF2 we decided that a better approach might be to compare stats to the player's previous successes, turning them from a worldwide comparative system into a personalized motivational one. The beginning player gets encouragement and acknowledgement that while they're not highly skilled yet, they're getting better all the time. The veterans get to see when they've managed to come close to their previous record, which encourages them beat that record.  The personal stat system also acts as a validation system. When a player feels like they've had a really good run, the stats system pops up and essentially says, 'You're right, that was a great run.'"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment029.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] Im bardziej grafika gry wykorzystuje jasne i sugestywne obiekty wizualne, tym mniej potrzeba wyjaśnień słownych. W najwcześniejszych wersjach TF2 grafika była bardzo realistyczna. Z czasem okazało się, że takie podejście powodowało szereg problemów.  Trudno było na przykład wystarczająco ukazać różnice między klasami graczy.  Trudno było także zwizualizować broń strzelającą czymkolwiek innym niż naboje.  Mapy były oderwane od rzeczywistości — raczej nie zdarzają się sytuacje, gdy dwie przeciwne siły budują obozy w odległości 20 metrów od siebie.  Ponadto pod względem wizualnym gra nie odróżniała się od naszych innych produktów.  W stylizowanym świecie nie ma takich problemów: postaw masywną postać Heavy obok ubranej w garnitur w paski postaci Spy, a gracze bez problemu zrozumieją zarówno liczbowe różnice dotyczące zdrowia istniejące między tymi klasami, jak i ich zupełnie różne style działania.  Testy pokazały, że gracze z łatwością zrozumieli ideę leczniczego strumienia wysyłanego przez lekarza, gdy tylko zobaczyli czerwone znaki plusa płynące do pacjenta.  Stylizowana fikcja naprawdę pozwala łatwo wyjaśnić, dlaczego bazy przeciwników leżą tak blisko siebie.  Wreszcie zrzut ekranu z gry TF2 jest bardzo łatwo rozpoznawalny — teraz nikt nie pomyli go z żadną inną grą."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment029.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] The more your art direction can use well-understood visual representations, the less work you have to do to explain your game elements. The earliest version of TF2 had a heavily realistic art direction. As time went on, we found this was causing us a lot of issues.  The differences between our player classes were hard to expose satisfactorily.  Weapons firing anything other than bullets were hard to visualize.  Our maps didn't make a lot of sense in the real world, where two opposing forces rarely build bases within fifty feet of one another.  In addition, the game wasn't visually distinct from our other products.  A stylized world had none of these problems:  Put the massive Heavy next to the pinstripe-suited Spy, and players understand both the numerical health differences between the classes and their very different gameplay styles.  The medic's healing beam was easily understood by playtesters when they saw the floating red plus symbols streaming into the target.  A stylized fiction can easily explain why the team's bases are built right next to each other.  Finally, a TF2 screenshot is easily recognizable, ensuring that no one will confuse it with another of our games."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment030.wav"   "[Moby Francke] Po podjęciu decyzji o przejściu w stronę stylizowanej szaty graficznej wypróbowaliśmy różne style, decydując się w końcu na wzorzec J.C. Leyendeckera, niezwykle popularnego ilustratora na początku XIX w. Sposób renderowania ubrań i materiałów przez Leyendeckera to doskonały przykład, jak nadać postaci szczegółowość, a jednocześnie zachować czyste, ostre kształty sylwetki, co ma kluczowe znaczenie w przypadku identyfikacji klas w naszej grze. Na podstawie zwykłych szablonów tak zaprojektowaliśmy pofałdowania ubrań, że na zbliżeniach widać odpowiednie szczegóły, ale bez zniekształcania wartości kolorów mających zwracać uwagę graczy na najważniejszą rzecz — broń."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment030.wav"   "[Moby Francke] Having decided on a stylized art direction, we experimented with a variety of styles before settling on the example of J.C. Leyendecker, an enormously popular illustrator of the early 1900s. Leyendecker's rendering of clothing and material provided a great example of how to add detail to a character while keeping the clean, sharp silhouette shapes that were key to our class identification. We used normal maps to craft folds of clothing, which provided a fine level of detail when seen up close, without detracting from color values meant to draw the player's eyes to the all-important weaponry."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment031.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] W grze wieloosobowej najważniejszym elementem graficznym są postacie, dlatego właśnie tutaj poświęciliśmy najwięcej wysiłków.  Opracowaliśmy hierarchię prezentacji danych o modelach, tzn. ustaliliśmy priorytety informacji, które gracze muszą być w stanie uzyskać jednym rzutem oka na model.  Oto ta hierarchia: 1. — drużyna, 2. — klasa, i 3. — obecnie używana broń.  Problematykę identyfikacji drużyny rozwiązano przez zastosowanie jednolitej palety kolorów dla każdej drużyny: ciepłe dla Czerwonych i zimne dla Niebieskich.  Przynależność do klas jest realizowana przez dobór sylwetek postaci. Unikatowe sylwetki i animowane kształty są lepiej rozpoznawane z dużych odległości i w większym zakresie warunków oświetleniowych niż jakiekolwiek inne szczegóły wizualne modelu. Z kolei problem odpowiedniego uwypuklenia broni rozwiązano za pomocą tekstur. Miejsca o najwyższym kontraście, które przyciągają wzrok graczy, zlokalizowano w okolicy klatki piersiowej modeli, czyli dokładnie tam, gdzie trzymają broń. Inny element przyciągający wzrok przeciwnika to subtelny gradient koloru: od ciemnego w okolicy stóp do jasnych miejsc na klatce piersiowej."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment031.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] Characters are the most important piece of art in a multiplayer game, so that is where we spent most of our effort.  We developed a read hierarchy for player models, prioritizing the information that players needed to be able to read merely by looking at the model.  Our hierarchy was this: first, what team they're on, second, what class they're playing, and third, what weapon they're wielding.  Team readability was addressed by adopting an overall color palette for each team, picking warm colors for Red and cool colors for Blu.  Class readability was addressed through the character's silhouette. Unique silhouette and animation shapes are more identifiable at far distances, and across a broader range of light levels, than any amount of other visual detail on the model. Finally, the weapon was highlighted through the textures. The areas of highest contrast, which attracts player's eyes, are all focused around the chest area of our character models, right where they hold their weapon. In addition, the subtle gradient from darkness around the character's feet, to the bright areas around the chest, also helps draw the player's eyes to the weapons."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment032.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] Strategia gry w TF2 opiera się na klasach graczy. Zastosowanie klas ma wiele zalet. Klasa ma ściśle ograniczony zasięg funkcjonalny, co pozwala na jej jednoznaczne odróżnienie od pozostałych klas. Gracz, który zmęczy się jedną klasą, może ją zmienić na inną i odzyskać w ten sposób chęć do grania. Klasy pozwalają uwzględnić różnorodność graczy pod względem umiejętności i preferowanych form działania. W jednej drużynie mogą z powodzeniem walczyć osoby początkujące i zaawansowane. Swoją niszę znajdą zarówno Ci, którzy lubią się długo zastanawiać, osoby z talentami do strategicznego planowania obrony czy fani skaczącej adrenaliny. Schemat klas w Team Fortress 2 pozwala zwiększyć ogólną pulę umiejętności zaangażowanych w rozgrywkę, a jednocześnie utrzymać rozsądny poziom zakresu decyzji podejmowania przez poszczególnych graczy."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment032.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] Player classes form the backbone of TF2's gameplay. There are a bunch of reasons why they're a useful design tool. A class is a bottled up experience, designed to be unique relative to the other classes in the game. A player who is getting tired of one class can switch to another class and get a fresh experience. They allow us to cater to players with a variety of different skills and desires. Beginning and advanced players can have fun together. Cautious cerebral thinkers, strategic defenders, and twitch firing adrenaline junkies can all find their niche. Team Fortress 2's Class design decisions enable us to have a larger number of player abilities in the game, while still keeping a single player's decisions down to a manageable level."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment033.wav"   "[Robin Walker] TF2 po raz pierwszy pokazaliśmy na targach E3 w roku 1999. Teraz mamy rok 2007. Co zajęło nam tak dużo czasu?  Krótko mówiąc, potrzebowaliśmy aż tyle czasu, żeby powstał produkt, z którego będziemy naprawdę zadowoleni.  Dłuższa odpowiedź wymagałaby przyjrzenia się całemu procesowi powstawania gry.  U jego podstawy leży założenie, iż z góry nie wiemy, które aspekty zdecydują o atrakcyjności gry.  Wiemy tylko, co sprawdziło się w poprzednich latach.  Jeśli jednak mamy na biurku trzy pomysły, nie jesteśmy w stanie stwierdzić na pewno, który z nich jest najlepszy.  Dlatego też postanowiliśmy opracować powtarzalny proces, który pozwoli nam dokonać takich ustaleń.  Opiera się on na sekwencji ciągłych iteracji, gdzie ocena jest dokonywana na podstawie obserwacji przebiegu gry z udziałem jak największej liczby osób.  W pracach nad TF2 wypróbowaliśmy mnóstwo funkcji. Wiele z nich trafiło do ostatecznej wersji produktu, ale większość została odrzucona.  Na przykład w pierwszych wersjach staraliśmy się zbudować fabułę wokół koncepcji dowódcy — jednej osoby, która na bieżąco ma strategiczny obraz całego pola bitwy.  Dowódca odpowiadał za budowane struktur i opracowywanie spójnej strategii dla całego zespołu.  Z takim podejściem wiązały się jednak zasadnicze problemy konstrukcyjne.  Na przykład: jak zaprojektować grę, aby jednocześnie dowódca i członkowie drużyny uczestniczący w bezpośrednim starciu czerpali przyjemność z rozgrywki?  Jak zagwarantować, aby dowódca i drużyna wzajemnie szanowali swój wkład?  Jak sprawić, aby gra dawała frajdę w przypadku, gdy kiepski dowódca dowodzi świetnym zespołem lub odwrotnie?  Przez wiele miesięcy pracowaliśmy nad tym i innymi zagadnieniami, i nigdy nie dotarliśmy do punktu, w którym bylibyśmy do końca zadowoleni.  Ponadto w wyniku prób dodania warstwy strategicznej na tyle głębokiej, aby w ogóle był sens wprowadzania postaci dowódcy, gra stała się nadmiernie skomplikowana.  W ostatecznym rozrachunku podjęliśmy ciężką, ale słuszną decyzję o usunięciu go z gry."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment033.wav"   "[Robin Walker] We first showed TF2 at E3 in 1999, and here we are in 2007. So what took us so long?  The short answer is that it took us this long to make something we were happy with.  The long answer requires a look at our development process.  At its core is the assumption that we don't really know ahead of time what will be fun.  We know what has been fun in the past.  But if we've got 3 ideas on the table, we can't say for sure which one will be the most fun.  So, we've focused on developing a repeatable process that will find out.  It's based on a cycle of constant iteration, where evaluation is done by watching as many people play the game as possible.  In developing TF2, we tried out many, many features-a few of which made it to the final product, but most of which were cut.  For example, our initial versions of TF2 were focused on trying to build a game around the concept of a commander, a single player who had a real-time-strategy view of the battlefield.  He was responsible for building structures and providing a unifying strategy for the team.  But there were significant design challenges involved.  For instance, how do we design the game such that the commander can have fun, and at same time ensure that the players down on the ground can have fun?  How do we ensure that the players & the commander value the output of the other?  How do we ensure that the game is still fun if you have a terrible commander, or conversely, if you're a great commander with a terrible team?  We spent many months working on these and other issues, and never reached a point where we were satisfied.  In addition, our game had become overly complex, due to our attempts to add a strategy layer deep enough to warrant the addition of the commander in the first place.  In the end, we made the hard decision to remove him from the game and moved on."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment034.wav"   "[Kelly Thornton] Jednym z efektów zwrócenia szczególnej uwagi na utrzymanie tempa gry było wprowadzenie funkcji śmiertelnych strzałów. System śmiertelnych strzałów ma na celu wywarcie pewnego wpływu na dynamikę gry przez zwiększenie/zmniejszenie szans na taki strzał w zależności od ostatnich osiągnięć gracza. Krótko mówiąc: im lepiej sobie radzisz, tym większe prawdopodobieństwo kontynuowania tego trendu. Dzięki temu istnieje szansa na te bardzo rzadkie sytuacje, gdy jeden gracz wpada w trans i zabija 3–4 przeciwników jednego po drugim."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment034.wav"   "[Kelly Thornton] Critical hits are one of the features that resulted from our focus on pacing. The critical hit system attempts to slightly influence the highs and lows of the game, by increasing the chance of a critical hit based upon the player's recent performance. In summary, the better you're doing, the more likely you'll continue to do well. This helps create those rare high moments, where a single player goes on a rampage and gets 3 or 4 kills in rapid succession."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment035.wav"   "[Adrian Finol] Jedną z najważniejszych zmian między Team Fortress Classic a Team Fortress 2 jest brak granatów ręcznych. W poprzedniej wersji członkowie większości klas mogli używać standardowych granatów ręcznych oraz dodatkowo granatów pomocniczych, związanych ściślej z daną klasą.  Gdy w Team Fortress 2 skupiliśmy się bardziej na unikatowych funkcjach poszczególnych klas, dostrzegliśmy, że zwykły granat ręczny miał większe znaczenie w walce niż niektóre rodzaje broni podstawowej.  W efekcie klasy miały bardziej zbliżoną zdolność bojową, co było niepożądane.  Ponadto gdy przyjrzeliśmy się sytuacjom patowym powstającym na niektórych mapach w Team Fortress Classic, często były wynikiem masowego posługiwania się granatami. Szczególnie problematyczne były dwa przypadki: gracze co chwila rzucający granaty przez otwory drzwiowe w nadziei na zabicie przeciwników po drugiej stronie oraz gracze na krawędzi śmierci rozrzucający dokoła wszystkie posiadane granaty w nadziei na zgładzenie wrogów już po swojej śmierci.  Wyeliminowanie standardowych granatów ręcznych niemal z miejsca uatrakcyjniło grę, szczególnie dla nowych graczy, którzy często nie wiedzieli, czemu giną, a przyczyną były właśnie granaty eksplodujące u ich stóp. Gdy przyjrzeliśmy się granatom unikatowym dla poszczególnych klas, zobaczyliśmy podobne problemy.  Dlatego na etapie testów usunęliśmy również te granaty, co znów wydatnie uprzyjemniło grę.  Po podjęciu decyzji o wyeliminowaniu granatów każdą klasę poddaliśmy analizie, aby sprawdzić, jakich możliwości ją pozbawiliśmy.  Jeśli stwierdziliśmy, że dana klasa straciła pewne ciekawe opcje decyzyjne, wprowadziliśmy funkcje kompensujące brak specjalistycznych granatów."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment035.wav"   "[Adrian Finol] One of the main changes between Team Fortress Classic and Team Fortress 2 was the removal of thrown grenades. 
Most classes could carry a standard hand grenade along with a secondary grenade, tied more closely to the class.  Team Fortress 2's focus on unique class roles led us to notice that the standard hand grenade was a more powerful combat decider than some of the primary weapons.  This made the classes more similar in combat-not a desired effect.  In addition, when we looked at some of Team Fortress Classic's map stalemates, they often resulted from large amounts of grenade spam. Two cases were particularly problematic:  That of players throwing grenades repeatedly through doorways, hoping to kill any enemies who might be there, and players on the verge of death throwing all their grenades in rapid succession, hoping to get a kill after they die.  Removing standard hand grenades made the game more fun almost immediately, especially for new players who were often confused as to why they died, when a grenade went off at their feet. When we examined the class-specific grenades, we found similar problems.  Eliminating them from playtests gave us yet another boost in making the game more fun.  Once we'd decided on removal, we analyzed each class to see what capabilities might have been lost as a result of the decision.  In some cases we added other capabilities, where we felt a class had lost the ability to make some interesting decisions, related to its special grenade type.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment036.wav"   "[Hamish McKenzie] Na końcowych etapach projektu, gdy różne moduły gry były już na ukończeniu, stwierdziliśmy, że mamy jeszcze trochę czasu na dodanie nieco animacji.  Było kilka pomysłów, w tym docinki na temat broni.  Oceniając przydatność danej funkcji, bierzemy pod uwagę jej powiązania z innymi funkcjami. Pod tym względem drwiny z broni były bezkonkurencyjne.  Dobrze współdziałają z funkcją migawek zabójcy gracza, wzmacniając relację między prześladowcą a jej ofiarą.  Animacje drwin z broni zajmuje prominentne miejsce, gdyż możemy w nich pokazać możliwości naszej nowej technologii animacji twarzy (gracze mogą oglądać twarz przeciwnika z każdej strony). Wreszcie, postacie w TF2 są bardzo wyraziste, a docinki na temat broni to doskonała okazja na ukazanie ich osobowości za pomocą animacji i modulowania głosu."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment036.wav"   "[Hamish McKenzie] Late in the project, while other parts of the game were being finished up, we found ourselves with some time left over for extra animation.  There were several ideas on the table, including weapon-specific taunt animations.  When evaluating a feature, we look at how many other features it connects to, and taunts were the clear winner.  They play well with the killer freeze-cam, adding to the relationship between the nemesis and his victim.  They gave us a highly visible place to show off our new facial animation technology, allowing the player to examine it from all angles. Finally, TF2's characters have a lot of personality, and taunts were the perfect way to show that personality through animation and voice acting."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment037.wav"   "[Eric Smith] W grze Half-Life 2 opracowaliśmy tzw. zasady reakcji. Jest to system umożliwiający szczegółowe dopasowanie sposobu wypowiadania linii dialogu przez postacie w reakcji na wydarzenia w grze, które są tylko częściowo przewidywalne.  W Team Fortress 2 zasady te zostały po raz pierwszy zastosowane w grze wieloosobowej.  System zasad reakcji działa następująco: reguły opisujące sposób artykulacji są umieszczone w zwykłym pliku tekstowym. Gdy warunki zdefiniowane w pliku wystąpią w grze, kod źródłowy gry sprawia, że postacie próbują mówić w określony sposób. Gdy na przykład gracz uzupełnia amunicję, jest to dla zasad reakcji sygnał, że warto, aby powiedział coś na ten temat. System zasad reakcji sprawdza stan otoczenia i przyporządkowuje mu zbiór reguł określających najlepszy tekst, jaki może paść w danym kontekście.  Jeśli zawodnik jest ranny, jego wypowiedź o uzupełnianiu amunicji może być inna niż w przypadku, gdy jest całkowicie zdrowy.  Innych słów użyje, gdy w ciągu ostatnich 20 sekund zabił więcej niż 2 wrogów, innych gdy znajduje się pod wodą itd.  Przechowywanie zapisów dialogów i zasad w plikach skryptów daje autorom gry możliwość dodawania tekstów mówionych bez konieczności ingerowania w kod źródłowy."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment037.wav"   "[Eric Smith] For Half-Life 2 we developed something called Response Rules, a system that lets us fine-tune the way characters speak lines of dialog in response to game events that are not completely predictable.  In Team Fortress 2, we extended Response Rules to the multiplayer environment for the first time.  The Response Rule system works by listing speech concepts in a simple text file; the game code then makes characters attempt to speak when the rules or conditions defined in the text file are met in the game. For instance, when a player reloads his weapon, this signals the Response Rule system that now would be an appropriate time to speak a line about reloading. The Response Rule system checks the state of the world, and matches it to a set of rules that determine the best line of dialog to use for that speech concept.  If the player's health is low, he may speak a different reloading line than if he is completely healthy.  He could play a special line if he has killed more than two enemies in the last 20 seconds, another set of lines if he's underwater, and so on.  Keeping dialog and rules in script files gives the game's writers the ability to add speech to the game without needing any code support.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment038.wav"   "[Moby Francke] We wstępnych dyskusjach poświęconych stylom renderowania postaci postanowiliśmy, że powinny one mieć charakter ilustracyjny (stylizowany), ale bez radykalizmu większości toon shaderów. Chcieliśmy, aby linie cieniowania były łagodniejsze niż przyjęło się dla tego typu renderowania.  Dlatego oświetlenie postaci wykonaliśmy za pomocą dwuwymiarowych tekstur, a w miejscu, gdzie spotykają się światło i cień, dodaliśmy nieco ciepła, dzięki czemu na przejściu pojawia się kolor. Po uzyskaniu odpowiedniego modelu cieniowania dodaliśmy do każdej postaci delikatną obwódkę. W ten sposób wokół sylwetek widać ładne podświetlenie, które pozwala odróżnić postacie na tle otaczającego trójwymiarowego świata."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment038.wav"   "[Moby Francke] In our early discussions of rendering styles for the characters, we decided we wanted them to have a look that was illustrative or stylized, without going to the extremes of most toon shaders. We wanted softer lines for shading than was typical for this sort of rendering.  So, we used a 2-D texture to define the lighting on the characters, and at the point where light and dark meet, we added a hint of warmth to give it that burst of color at the transition. Once we had achieved the right shading model, we added a rim-term to the characters, so they would have a nice highlight around the edges of their silhouettes, which helps them to stand out from the surrounding 3d world."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment039.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] Problemem przy konstruowaniu systemu cząsteczkowego było stworzenie efektów, które były ciekawe i atrakcyjne wizualnie, ale na tyle dyskretne, aby nie przesłoniły sensu całej gry.  W typowej walce na ekranie w jednym czasie jest tyle efektów wizualnych, że największym niebezpieczeństwem jest chaos optyczny.  Dlatego też postanowiliśmy, że w naszej grze efekty powinny być prostsze i bardziej przejrzyste.  Efekty najważniejsze dla przebiegu gry są najłatwiej widoczne, natomiast te, które mają tylko ładnie wyglądać przesunięto na dalszy plan.  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment039.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] The challenge of the particle system was to create effects that were fun and visually exciting, without being so 'over the top' that no one could read their meaning in the game.  In a typical match, there are so many effects onscreen at the same time, that the biggest danger is visual clutter.  Therefore, the effects were refined to be cleaner and simpler.  Those that were most important for gameplay were made easier to see, while those that were mainly eye-candy were allowed to fall into the background.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment040.wav"   "[Robin Walker] Przy dziewięciu klasach postaci oraz ogromnej różnorodności broni i unikatowych umiejętności jednym z największych wyzwań było udostępnienie wszystkich tych kombinacji graczom w sposób użyteczny, a nie przytłaczający.  Nawet krótka lista podstawowych informacji budzi respekt: cele na mapach, rozmieszczenie członków swojej drużyny, kto strzela z jakiej broni itd.  Ponieważ nie dało się w żaden sposób przekazać tych informacji wizualnie, najpierw musieliśmy ustalić listę i priorytety najważniejszych rzeczy, które powinien znać każdy uczestnik, aby czerpać przyjemność z gry.  Informacje możliwe do uzyskania w trakcie samej gry, np. układ mapy, miały znaczenie drugorzędne. Istniały jednak także informacje, np. o zastrzyku nieśmiertelności ordynowanym przez lekarza, które byłyby całkowicie niewidoczne, gdybyśmy nie zwrócili na nie wyraźnej uwagi.  W miarę możliwości staraliśmy się uniknąć dołączania dwuwymiarowych elementów do wyświetlacza przeziernego, ponieważ chcieliśmy, aby gracze patrzyli na stworzony dla nich trójwymiarowy świat, a nie jakąś abstrakcyjną prezentację.  Na przykład: gracze zawsze widzą szpiegów z własnej drużyny jako szpiegów, ale muszą znać przebranie, jakiego używają oni wobec przeciwników.  Próbowaliśmy pójść na skróty, umieszczając nad głową szpiega ikonę ilustrującą jego aktualne przebranie.  Gracze, którzy testowali taką wersję, byli zdezorientowani.   Kiedy w odpowiedzi ikony zastąpiliśmy wyciętymi papierowymi maskami nakładanymi przez szpiegów na twarze, nie tylko zgrabnie wpasowały się one w humorystyczną naturę gry, ale pozwoliły graczom zdobywać wszystkie niezbędne informacje jednym rzutem oka, a w efekcie bardziej skupić się na całości postaci i przebiegu gry.  Potraktowaliśmy to jako lekcję — jak trzymanie się ścisłych, przemyślanych założeń projektowych często prowadzi do lepszych rozwiązań niż obranie drogi na skróty."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment040.wav"   "[Robin Walker] With nine classes of characters, and so many weapons and unique abilities, one of our biggest challenges was exposing all these combinations to players without overwhelming them.  Even the shortlist of essential information is intimidating, including map goals, the whereabouts of their friends, who's shooting them with what weapon, and so on.  We didn't have any way to make all of this information visual, so first we had to prioritize and come up with an essential list of things every player needed to know in order to just have fun.  Information they could learn by playing the game-such as map layout-was of secondary importance; but there was also information, such as the Medic's invulnerability charge, that would be completely invisible unless we exposed it.  We tried to avoid attaching 2D elements to the HUD as much as possible, since we wanted players to be looking at the 3D world we'd built rather than some abstract representation.  For example, players always see their own team's spies as a spy, but they need to know how the spy is disguised to the other team.  We tried a quick hack where we put an icon representing the spy's current disguise floating above his head.  The icon proved baffling to playtesters.   When we tackled the problem by putting cut-out paper masks on the spy, it not only fit the humorous style of the game, but it let players get all pertinent information directly from a quick look at the spy's model, thus keeping them focused on the characters and on the action of the game.  We took this as a lesson, in how holding ourselves to a strong design principle can often force us to come up with better solutions, than if we'd taken the easy route."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment041.wav"   "[Jason Mitchell] żołnierz do tego miejsca: setpos 281,531250 3295,468750 -124,027405;setang 4,553997 176,268036 0,000000 Aby uzyskać styl cieniowania zbliżony do ilustracji z reklam z początków XX wieku, na których oparliśmy grafikę gry, zmieniliśmy sposób rozpraszania światła na postaciach. Tutaj widać żołnierza z Team Fortress 2, dla którego zastosowano właśnie ów ilustracyjny styl cieniowania. Proszę zwrócić uwagę na wyraźne przejście między jasną i ciemną stroną, gdy pada na niego światło z sąsiedniego pomieszczenia. Jeśli (jak na przykładzie) zostanie użyte tradycyjne oświetlenie [wartość parametru r_identitylightwarp równa 1], oświetlenie postaci jest zbyt miękkie i nie odpowiada założonemu ilustracyjnemu stylowi. Przy ilustracyjnym modelu oświetlenia [wartość parametru r_identitylightwarp równa 0] postać jest doświetlona w sposób, który znacznie lepiej odpowiada całościowemu stylowi graficznemu.  żołnierz z tyłu do tego miejsca (ciemny narożnik w pobliżu pozycji powyżej): setpos 482,125000 3267,843750 -124,027405;setang -1,386003 -137,399948 0,000000 Kolejnym elementem ilustracyjnego cieniowania jest zastosowanie podświetlanych obwódek, które podkreślają zarys postaci na tle otoczenia. Bez obwódki [wartość parametru r_rimlight równa 0] postać wtapia się w tło. Dzięki obwódce [wartość parametru r_rimlight równa 1] postacie są dobrze widoczne na tle scenerii oraz lepiej pasują do artystycznego stylu całej gry."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment041.wav"   "[Jason Mitchell] soldier up to here: setpos 281.531250 3295.468750 -124.027405;setang 4.553997 176.268036 0.000000 To achieve a style of character shading which is consistent with the early 20th Century commercial illustrations that influenced our art direction, we alter the diffuse lighting on characters. Here, we can see the Soldier as he appears in Team Fortress 2, using our illustrative shading style. Note the tight transition between the light and dark sides of the Soldier as he is lit by the light in the next room. Using traditional lighting [set r_identitylightwarp to 1] as seen here, the character lighting appears too soft and does not fit our illustrative style. With the illustrative lighting model [set r_identitylightwarp to 0], our characters are lit in a way which better fits our overall art style.  back soldier up to here (dark corner near above position): setpos 482.125000 3267.843750 -124.027405;setang -1.386003 -137.399948 0.000000 Another facet of illustrative shading is the use of rim highlights to accentuate the silhouettes of characters to keep them from blending into the scenery. Without the rim lighting [set r_rimlight to 0], the character blends into the background. With the rimlighting, [set r_rimlight to 1] characters are visible against the rest of the scene and better fit the art style of Team Fortress 2."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment042.wav"   "[Alden Kroll] Dwuwymiarowe elementy na wyświetlaczach przeziernych stanowią szczególny problem z perspektywy wyrazu artystycznego, ponieważ muszą być ładne i wyraźne niezależnie od aktualnej rozdzielczości. Przy obecnych szerokokątnych monitorach o wysokiej rozdzielczości spełnienie tego wymogu oznacza znaczne obciążenie pamięci obsługą tekstur oraz przygotowania na bardzo wiele różnych rozdzielczości. W TF2 problem ten był jeszcze bardziej odczuwalny, ponieważ zamierzaliśmy wbudować w wyświetlaczu szereg elementów o łagodnych krzywiznach. Dlatego też opracowaliśmy zupełnie nowy system cieniowania służący do rysowania szkiców.  Umożliwia on generowanie obrazów o ustalonej rozdzielczości, które zachowują płynność sylwetek nawet przy jej znacznym zwiększeniu. Ponadto system ten odpowiada za generowanie konturów i cieni rzucanych przez obiekty i postacie. Można go używać w przestrzeni trójwymiarowej do różnych elementów otoczenia, np. znaków.  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment042.wav"   "[Alden Kroll] Two-dimensional HUD elements present a particular art problem, because they have to look good and sharp no matter what resolution the user is running their game at. Given today's availability of high resolution wide-screen displays, this can require a lot of texture memory and a lot of work anticipating different display resolutions. The problem for TF2 was even more daunting because of our desire to include a lot of smooth curved elements in our HUD. We developed a new shader system for drawing 'line art' images.  The system allows us to create images at a fixed resolution that produced smooth silhouettes even when scaled up to a very high resolution. This shader system also handles outlining and drop-shadows, and can be applied in the 3D space to world elements such as signs.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment043.wav"   "[Chris Green] W Team Fortress 2 postanowiliśmy zastosować szereg specjalnych efektów cząsteczkowych, które zwiększałyby możliwości różnych typów broni i klas. W poprzednich wersjach aparatu obsługującego kod źródłowy wszystkie efekty musiały być jednostkowo wpisywane przez programistów. Dla Team Fortress 2 stworzyliśmy system, w którym projektanci mogą błyskawicznie tworzyć nowe systemy cząsteczkowe oraz iteracyjnie dopracowywać istniejące systemy bez jakiegokolwiek udziału programistów. Wbudowany edytor umożliwia edytowanie definicji systemów i natychmiastowe sprawdzanie efektów wprowadzonych zmian w samej grze.  Ponadto opcje zawarte w edytorze pozwalają artystom na łączenie modułowych „elementów konstrukcyjnych” efektów, tworząc bardziej skomplikowane formy. Jeśli chodzi o sam system cząsteczkowy, wiele wykonywanych przez niego obliczeń przenieśliśmy do akceleratora graficznego, co pozwoliło zwiększyć liczbę cząsteczek na ekranie przy zachowaniu szybkości odtwarzania klatek."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment043.wav"   "[Chris Green] We intended Team Fortress 2 to feature many special particle effects to enhance the wide variety of weapons and class abilities. In previous versions of the Source engine, all particle effects required that custom code be written by the programmers. For Team Fortress 2, we created a system where designers can rapidly create new particle systems and iteratively refine existing ones, without programmer involvement. An in-game editor allows designers to edit the definitions of particle systems and immediately preview effects in the game itself.  The editor also allows artists to connect modular effect 'building blocks' to create complex visual effects. As for the particle system itself, we have offloaded many of the system calculations to the graphics accelerator, which allows us to increase the number of particles onscreen without reducing the framerate."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment044.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Gdy już ustaliliśmy styl graficzny dla naszego świata i postaci, skierowaliśmy uwagę na broń i gadżety. O ile obiekty odwołują się w pewnym zakresie do przedmiotów znanych ze świata realnego, zazwyczaj mocno się od nich różnią. Na przykład wyrzutnia rakiet używana przez żołnierzy zasadniczo odpowiada prawdziwej ręcznej wyrzutni rakiet, a jednak jakimś cudem mieści cztery pociski. Aby usprawiedliwić takie nieścisłości i nie psuć zabawy w świecie naszej stylizowanej fikcji, wszystkie rodzaje broni z założenia wyglądają jak niestandardowe — spersonalizowane i zmodyfikowane przez każdego użytkownika pod kątem własnych potrzeb. Trzymając się industrialnego motywu gry, projekty głównych rodzajów broni oparliśmy na motywach z lat 60-tych. Z kolei jako wzorzec dla broni pomocniczej i do walki w zwarciu wykorzystaliśmy instrumenty muzyczne, ponieważ uznaliśmy, że podkreślą one związek między ową bronią a osobowością postaci."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment044.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Once we had a handle on the art direction for our world and characters, we turned our attention to the weapons and gadgets. While these objects have some grounding in reality, they usually diverge in significant ways. For instance, the soldier's rocket launcher fits the general mold of a shoulder mounted rocket launcher, but somehow manages to hold four rockets in a clip. To justify this, and play up our stylized Spy-tech fiction, we designed the weapons to look like customized pieces of hardware, personalized and modified by each character to suit his own ends. In keeping with the industrial theme of the game, we looked to 60's era product design principles for the primary weapons, then focused on musical instruments for secondary and melee weapons, thinking these would reinforce the connection between the secondary items and each character's personality."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment045.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] Projektując miejsca, w których ma dochodzić do starć, próbujemy uniknąć nadmiernej złożoności i chaosu.  Skomplikowany kształt terenu przeszkadza graczom, utrudniając śledzenie wroga oraz przemieszczanie się własnych jednostek i celowanie. Najbardziej chaotyczne walki mają miejsce w przypadku, gdy pomieszczenie jest za małe dla wszystkich znajdujących się w nim osób.  Chcieliśmy, aby w ostatnim fragmencie mapy doszło do otwartej bitwy, która doprowadziłaby do ostatecznego wyłonienia zwycięzcy.  W tym celu przygotowaliśmy otwarty teren z kilkoma wejściami oraz udostępniliśmy graczom różne opcje ataku i obrony na różnych wysokościach. Zamiast wind i drabin zastosowaliśmy pochylnie, ponieważ tylko one zapewniają swobodę ruchu przez cały czas.  Na skutek przeprowadzonych testów wprowadziliśmy wiele modyfikacji w rozmiarach pomieszczenia, obiektów mogących stanowić zasłonę i otworów wejściowych, tak aby w walce mogło uczestniczyć naprawdę wielu graczy.  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment045.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] When designing areas for high levels of combat, we try to avoid complexity and chaos.  Complex geometry confuses players, making it hard for them to track enemies, and interfering with their movement and aiming during combat. The most chaotic combat tends to occur when the size of the room fails to support the number of players fighting in it.  In this final area of the map, we wanted a freeform battle to rage for some time before anyone could achieve a decisive victory.  To achieve this, we built a wide open area with several entrances, and gave players a variety of attack and defense options at various heights. Rather than depend on elevators and ladders, we relied on ramps, since these allow freedom of movement at all times instead of confining players.  Through playtesting we made many changes to the dimensions of the room, the size of cover elements, and the size of the entrances, thus ensuring the area could accommodate a battle of many players.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment046.wav"   "[Aaron Barber] W odróżnieniu od map w TF takich jak 2fort czy Well, których boki są oznaczone niebieskim i czerwonym kolorem o rosnącej intensywności, cztery główne obszary na mapie Hydro mogą być opanowane w całości przez jeden z zespołów. Potrzebowaliśmy ogólnego motywu, który pasowałby do istniejących obiektów, takich jak kamienne mury czy tunele, ale który miałby również neutralny schemat kolorów. Dlatego wybraliśmy motyw pustynny z paletą czerwonawo-brązowych skał, zimnoniebieskie niebo oraz oświetlenie w neutralnych kolorach, które uzupełnia otaczający krajobraz. Kolory poszczególnych obszarów różnią się nieco między sobą, ale tworzą spójną całość."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment046.wav"   "[Aaron Barber] Unlike maps in TF such as 2fort and Well, which have progressively blue and red sides, Hydro's four main arenas can be owned by one team or the other. We needed an overall theme that justified structures like rock walls and tunnels, but which also had a neutral color scheme. We chose a desert theme with a palette of reddish-brown rock, cool blue sky and neutral light colors that complement the surrounding area. The colors of the seperate areas vary slightly but still key together.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment047.wav"   "[Chet Faliszek] Narrator w grze Team Fortress 2, Ellen McLain, jest jedyną aktorką, która podkłada głos we wszystkich grach kolekcji Orange.  W grze Team Fortress 2 Ellen próbowała różnej intonacji tych samych linii tekstu, pokazując w ten sposób różne osobowości.  Przy piątej próbie wreszcie jej się udało. Jej rozczarowany, zawsze nieco zdenerwowany, zły władca jasno daje do zrozumienia, że w świecie Team Fortress remis nie oznacza, że wszyscy wygrywają, ale że wszyscy przegrywają."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment047.wav"   "[Chet Faliszek] The announcer for Team Fortress 2, Ellen McLain, has the rare distinction of being the only voice actor to perform in all the products in the Orange box.  For her role in Team Fortress 2, we had Ellen try various reads on the same lines letting her ad-lib different personalities.  On the 5th try, she came up with the winner. Her disappointed and slightly angry evil overlord clearly lets you know, in the world of Team Fortress a tie does not mean everyone wins, but that everyone loses."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment048.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] Ten obszar sprawiał szczególne problemy. Ponieważ większość scenerii to wnętrza pomieszczeń, nie mogliśmy za wiele zrobić w kierunku zmiany jej podstawowej struktury. Dlatego skoncentrowaliśmy się na uporządkowaniu kształtów wewnątrz i stworzeniu przestrzeni zdefiniowanej za pomocą ikon. Budynek to zasadniczo prostopadłościan z dużymi prostokątnymi oknami, z którym kontrastują okrągłe elementy (generatory) w środkowej części. Aby uzyskać efekt głębi i paralaksy, dodaliśmy elementy liniowe, takie jak poręcze i kable. Na podłodze zastosowaliśmy mieszankę kontrastowych jasnych i ciemnych kolorów, które m.in. wyznaczają ścieżki. Wszystkie te elementy mają na celu przyciągnięcie wzroku gracza do flagi, która zawsze musi być dla niego najważniejszym punktem na arenie walki."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment048.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] This area presented a difficult problem. Since the arena is primarily an interior, there wasn't much we could do to alter its basic structure, so we concentrated on careful management of the interior shapes to create an iconic space. The building is essentially a box with big rectangular windows, contrasted by round elements (generators) in the center. To create depth and parallax, we added linear elements such as railings and cables. We used contrasting values of dark and light on the floor, with walkways to create an interesting value pattern. All these elements work together to draw the player's eye to the flag--which must always be the focal point of the arena."
}
}
